"Plant-Based Diets Could Save Millions of
Lives and Trillions of Dollars a Year"
Based on a meta-analysis
of studies following
millions of people
and their diets for years,
better adherence
to more plant-based diets,
especially ones emphasizing
healthy plant foods,
is beneficial
for lowering the risks
of major chronic conditions,
including type 2 diabetes,
cardiovascular disease,
and cancer,
as well as premature death
in general.
Moving to diets with
fewer animal-sourced foods
could end up saving the lives of
millions of people every year,
in addition to saving
trillions of dollars.
Here’s how many lives might be
saved by a healthy global diet,
which is like more of
a Mediterranean cut-down-on-red
meat-and-sugar,
eat-lots-of-fruits-
and-vegetables diet,
versus a vegetarian diet,
versus a vegan diet.
So, we’re talking
major health benefits
eating fewer
animal-sourced foods:
Healthier diets could save
five million lives a year.
If the world went vegetarian,
we’d save seven million lives
a year,
and if the world
started eating vegan,
we might save eight million
lives per year.
So, the question is less "what
to do" and more "how to do it."
In other words, the main problem
is the implementation gap,
which is likely a result
of things like inertia,
individual addictions,
commercial interests,
and economic issues.
For example, why did
the World Health Organization
pull support from a global
initiative promoting
more plant-based foods?
Yeah, eating that way might save
millions of lives,
but a global move to such a diet
could lead to the loss
of millions of jobs
linked to animal agriculture.
"’[T]he total
or nearly total elimination
of foods of animal origin
would destroy cattle farming
and many other activities
related to the production
of meat and dairy products."
"The initiative ’urging
for a centralized control
of our dietary choices’
risked ’the total elimination of
consumers’ freedom of choice."
And that was the reaction
to just recommending
people try eating
more plant-based.
And hey,
that’s just meat and dairy.
Think of how many jobs in
the candy and liquor industries
would be lost if people
all of a sudden decided
to eat and drink healthier.
It could have
drastic consequences.
There is a reason
that soda companies sponsor
major health organizations.
Over a five-year period,
researchers found that the
Coca-Cola Company and PepsiCo
sponsored "a total of 96
national health organizations
in United States,
including many medical
and public health institutions
whose specific missions include
fighting the obesity epidemic."
The American Academy of Family
Physicians took their money,
the American Academy
of Pediatrics, the AMA,
the dietitians,
the Society
for Nutrition Educators.
Maybe the soda companies
genuinely care
about the public’s health?
Hardly.
During the same study period,
those same two corporations
lobbied against
29 public health bills intended
to reduce soda consumption
or improve nutrition.
Although national food
guidelines are designed,
ostensibly, to translate
scientific evidence
with respect to food,
dietary patterns, and health,
their development
has increasingly become
a corporate
and political process
as much as scientific one,
often with corporate
and political influences
overriding the science.
As I detailed before,
this goes back all the way
to the first edition
of the American food goals
which started out
strongly recommending
decreasing our intake of meat,
dairy, and eggs
to reduce saturated fat,
as well as reducing
salt and sugar intake.
However, lobbyists
reacted vehemently
and succeeded in having the
wording in the report changed
to "increase the consumption
of lean meat."
Thus, the year in which
protecting public health
in the United States
became secondary to protecting
corporate health and wealth
was 1977.
Now, nearly 50 years later,
the efforts of the dietary
guidelines advisory committee
is recognized
for all the work they do,
but despite these achievements,
some key recommendations
in the current guidelines
do not reflect
the best available evidence
that "strongly support shifting
toward lower consumption
of animal protein sources
and higher intakes
of healthy plant sources."
But it’s such a politically
hot-button issue
that even when it comes
to the worst of the worst--
processed meats,
like bacon, ham, hot dogs,
lunch meat, and sausage--
known to cause cancer
in human beings,
yet all we have are provisos
"to consume these carcinogenic
foods ’in moderation.’"
Given that there may be no safe
limit for alcohol consumption,
the Canadian guidelines advise
no more than
one to two drinks a week.
Its dietary guidelines
were updated
to emphasize
the importance of consuming
more plant-based products,
and even removed dairy
as its own food group.
How were the Canadians so free
to be able
to better follow the evidence?
They decided to remove
industry-funded studies
from their consideration.
What a concept.
If we were going to try
to stick to the best science,
the eating pattern that is
healthiest for humans,
the one that best reduces
the risk of our leading killers,
would be a diet centered
around whole plant foods.
The reason we don’t see this
in national food guide
recommendations
can be explained by factors
other than science,
specifically,
corporate interests
reflected in heavily
government-subsidized
animal-sourced products
and the political might of the
ultra-processed food industry.
A whole food, plant-based diet
might be considered
the dietary gold standard
against which other dietary
patterns could be compared,
if for no other reason
than it’s the only diet
that has been shown
to reliably reverse
the progression
of coronary atherosclerosis,
the number-one killer
of men and women.
What else do we need?
So, if we wanted an unbiased,
evidence-based
Universal Food Guide,
if might look
a little something like this.
And for those of you thinking,
hey, that looks kinda familiar,
that’s because
it’s the Daily Dozen.
So, you can use
the free
Dr. Greger’s Daily Dozen app
as a reminder to fit some of
the healthiest of healthy foods
into your daily routine.